<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A testimony against periwigs and periwig making, and playing on instruments of musick among Christians or any other in the days of the gospel being several reasons against those things / by one who for good conscience sake hath denyed and forsaken them, John Mulliner.</title>
            <author>Mulliner, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1677</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 53 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51587</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M3059</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31060</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11770071</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11770071</idno>
            <idno type="VID">48840</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51587)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48840)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1489:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A testimony against periwigs and periwig making, and playing on instruments of musick among Christians or any other in the days of the gospel being several reasons against those things / by one who for good conscience sake hath denyed and forsaken them, John Mulliner.</title>
                  <author>Mulliner, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>14 [i.e. 22] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1677.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Contains numerous errors in pagination.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages stained with slight loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works.</term>
               <term>Clothing and dress --  Social aspects.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:48840:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48840:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TESTIMONY Againſt Periwigs and Periwig-Making, and Playing on Inſtruments of Muſick among CHRISTIANS, or any other in the days of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>Being ſeveral Reaſons againſt thoſe things, By one, who for Good Conſcience ſake hath denyed and forſaken them, <hi>John Mulliner.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>But God forbid that I ſhould glory, ſave in the Croſs of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt by whom the world is crucified unto me, and I unto the world
<bibl>
                     <hi>Gal. 6.14.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>But ſhe that liveth in pleaſure, is dead while ſhe liveth,
<bibl>
                     <hi>1 Tim. 5.6</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Wo to the Crown of Pride, <bibl>
                     <hi>Iſa. 38.1.</hi>
                  </bibl> Wo to them that are at eaſe in Zion. &amp; truſt in the mountain of Samaria, which are named chief of the nations to whom the houſe of Iſrael came. Paſſe ye unto Calneh and ſee and from thence go ye to Hemath the great; then go down to Gath of the Philiſtines, be they better then theſe kingdoms? or their border greater then your border? Ye that put far away the evil day &amp; cauſe the ſeat of violence to come near: That lie upon beds of ivory, and ſtretch themſelves upon their couches and eat the lambs out of the flock and the calves out of the midſt of the ſtall: That chaunt to the ſound of the viol and invent to themſelves inſtruments of muſick like David: That drink wine in bowls, and anoint themſelves with the chief ointments: but they are not grieved for the affliction of Joſeph.
<bibl>
                     <hi>Amos 6.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>It is better to go to the Houſe of Mourning then to go the Houſe of Feaſting; for that is the end of all men, and the living will lay it to heart. Sorrow is better then Laughter, for by the ſadneſs of the Countenance, the heart is made better,
<bibl>
                     <hi>Eccleſ. 7.2, 3.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Year 1677</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:48840:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:48840:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Reaſons why <hi>John Mulliner</hi> Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber in <hi>Northampton,</hi> left off his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment of <hi>Borders</hi> and <hi>Periwig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>making,</hi> and how it was with him, as to his <hi>Inward Condition</hi> before he Joyned with the People of God, in ſcorn called <hi>Quakers;</hi> as alſo his Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony for them, and his <hi>earneſt Deſires</hi> to his Neighbours and Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the Town of <hi>Northampton,</hi> that they would as well as himſelf, be reconciled to the Principle of God in their Conſcience, now after this Judgment of God that hath been upon this Town by Fire</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Loving Neighbours and Acquaintance,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>SInce I have left off my Imployment of making Borders and Periwigs, it hath occaſioned ſeveral of you to ſpeak hardly of me, and many Reports there are and have been concerning of it, inſomuch that I have been told, <hi>I have made my ſelf a Town and Country-talk.</hi> Now for the clearing of my ſelf and the Truth of God
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:48840:3"/>
in which I am concerned, and your Underſtandings, it hath been much in my Mind to acquaint you with the Reaſons why I left it, which I would fain have avoyded, and not to appeared ſo openly amongſt you, for I have ſent ſeveral Letters to ſome Perſons whom <hi>I</hi> have been concerned with, in Town and Country, to let them know why <hi>I</hi> left them; but this would not ſatisfie me, but as <hi>I</hi> have been a publick Profeſſor of this Employment for many years, <hi>I</hi> found <hi>I</hi> could not be clear in the ſight of God and man, till <hi>I</hi> had publickly given my Reaſon why I left it off; and likewiſe how it was with me, as to my inward Codition, before I joyned with this People of God, who are in Scorn called <hi>Quakers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ever ſince I was about ten or twelve years of age, that <hi>I</hi> began to think that there was a God, it hath been my earneſt Breathing deſire, to know Peace with him; and often when I was walking in the field, I have thought, that the very Fowls of the Air, and the Beaſts of the Field were in a better Condition then <hi>I</hi> was, if <hi>I</hi> did not know Peace with God when my Dayes were at an End: And it hath been my ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Cry to God, in the time of my Apprentiſhip and ſince, as <hi>I</hi> have been walking in the Field &amp; other Places, as I have been in private by myſelf, that <hi>I had rather have my HELL, or Sorrrw &amp; Trouble here in this life, then to endure the Everlaſting DISPLEAS<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RE of the God of Heaven hereafter;</hi> and in order to this good deſire, which was begotten in me by the Lord, I did love to wirte Sermons, &amp; to hear the beſt of Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers as I thought then, which I have gone two Miles to hear, in the time of my Apprentiſhip, rather then I would have gone to ſport or play my time away; and at that time, as I have been going, I have cryed and begged of God, <hi>That I might not miſs of ſomething that might be for my Soul's good, when my dayes were at an End:</hi> And after this manner have I gone out in thoſe dayes; and ſince I came to the Town of <hi>Northampton</hi> to ſet up for my Trade, I was a great Hearer of <hi>Simon Ford,</hi> who belonged to the Pariſh of <hi>Albollows;</hi> and I have writ his Sermons, and after <hi>I</hi> had done, <hi>I</hi> have come home and locked my ſelf in, and took my Bible and read the Scriptures, and after <hi>I</hi> have read his Sermons, and have laid them before me, and have knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led down and cryed and prayed to God, that if there was any thing in them, whereby <hi>I</hi> might come to the Knowledge of God's Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Truth, that he would not <hi>Withhold himſelf from me, that I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ght have an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding of it; For Lord (I</hi> have ſaid) <hi>thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:48840:3"/>
my Deſire is before thee, and that I did not beg for any thing in this life, but for my Soul's Peace with thee, when my dayes were at an End:</hi> And the more <hi>I</hi> prayed and cryed, the more Trouble <hi>I</hi> had; ſo that <hi>I</hi> knew not what to do <hi>I</hi> was ſo much diſtreſſed; but <hi>I</hi> thought to go to <hi>Simon Ford,</hi> who was my Teacher, in hopes he would have ſatisfied me, but finding that <hi>I</hi> could not declare my Condition, as <hi>I</hi> had felt it upon my Spirit for ſome time, <hi>I</hi> took a ſheet of Paper and writ my Condition, and read it to him, how that <hi>I</hi> was in great trouble night and day, ſo that <hi>I</hi> could not tell what to do, though <hi>I</hi> had writ his Sermons, and laid them before me, and cryed and prayed to God, that he would give me a true Underſtanding of his way, that <hi>I</hi> might have my Soul ſaved when my dayes were at an End: And much more <hi>I</hi> did write to this Purpoſe, which writing ſome of my Neighbours at that time did ſee, as <hi>I</hi> ſhewed it to them: So he confeſſed, theſe were good deſires, and could ſay little againſt me, but after pretty much diſcourſe to this Purpoſe, he adviſed me to read a Book, which <hi>I</hi> did get and read it; but no Comfort could <hi>I</hi> get from him nor the Book neither though <hi>I</hi> went to him and ſeveral more of that Coat, ſeveral times, before <hi>I</hi> joyned with this People called <hi>Quakers:</hi> And <hi>I</hi> was ſatisfied that there was that in me that time, that no man could ſatisfie, except the God of Heaven appear in h m: And ſometimes <hi>I</hi> have ſeen this People, when they have come amongſt us, when <hi>I</hi> was a Hearer of <hi>Simon Ford,</hi> into the very Aſſemblies, and though they have ſaid very little, what a Confuſion was there among the Teachers and Hearers! And ſometimes <hi>I</hi> have ſeen them, two or three that came into this Place, which was ſuffered by the Judgment through Fire to be laid waſte, that they have come into the Aſſembly at <hi>Albal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows,</hi> with Sack-cloth and Aſhes upon their Heads, bare-foot and bare-headed, which I did at that very time, very much ſtrange at: And another time <hi>I</hi> ſaw ano her come into the School, when they were act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their pa ts in ſtrange Dreſſes, and wiſhed them, to train up their Children <hi>in the Fear of the Lord;</hi> and they did lay violently upon him with their Sticks, ſo that I was much troubled to ſee it: And ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral times <hi>I</hi> have cryed and prayed to God to know why was it ſo, that this People came amongſt us after this manner; what is the matter with them? notwithſtanding though it be ſo, and they are never ſo uncomely, yet if this be thy People, give me an Underſtanding con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning of it; for thou knowſt what my ſoul travels after: And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:48840:4"/>
I joyned with them, it was very hard for me to deny my ſelf and become a Fool, by reaſon of my great Acquaintance and Buſineſs, in way of my Trade: <hi>I thought</hi> I <hi>did not care if I had been of any Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſo I had not been of that:</hi> Many of my Acquaintance would make a Mock at me; ſo one time I purpoſed to go to <hi>Halſon Horſe Race,</hi> about two Miles off <hi>Northampton,</hi> &amp; then if went thither, I thought they would not take notice of me for ſuch an one; but as ſoon as <hi>I</hi> come <hi>I</hi> thought they took notice of me, and ſaid, <hi>What, we hear you are turned Quaker:</hi> but the Lord knew what Pain my ſoul was in at that time; but I thought long to get by my ſelf to cry and pray to God; and come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing home my Brother M. came with me; for <hi>I</hi> know his very heart was concerned for me at that time; but there was ſuch a Load and Pain fell upon me at that time that made me cry out with many tears running down my Cheeks, <hi>Lord God of Heaven have Mercy upon me, what ſhall I do to be ſaved? Lord God of Heaven have Mercy upon me, what ſhall I do to be ſaved?</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o he fell a crying to me and ſaid, <hi>What ayleth thee Brother the Lord will have Mercy upon thee:</hi> And I knew not any one living in all the world that could afford me any Comfort, except the God of Heaven did. Neighbours &amp; Acquaintance, I write no Lye to you this day, God is my witneſs; and ſo long (I do believe) as my Brother hath Life and Senſe, he will not forget that time, as he hath told me ſince: And about this time there were ſeveral of this People carried out dead out of the County Goal, which lay in the Dungeon, FOR THE TESTIMONY OF JESUS; which I know not, but might be by Reaſon of the Straitneſs of the Place as they were confined in and for want of common Air: And then I began to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire what was the matter, and I could not underſtand that any thing was laid to their Charge, except it was as concerning the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of their God; and then I wiſhed, if they ſuffered for God's ſake and for Righteouſneſs ſake, that <hi>I</hi> might ſuffer with them too; for I did not care if they burned me, if <hi>I</hi> was ſure it was for God's ſake; but all the Buſineſs was to know whether <hi>I</hi> ſhould be ſure of it: So J diſcourſed with ſome of my Neighbours and Acquaintance, &amp; they ſaid it was a Fancy and a Whimſie, Bewitching and Deluſion; and after this rate they talked; but the Lord knew my heart, was it a Whimſie, and Deluſion, and Bewitching, to cry and pray to God to have Mercy upon my ſoul, when my dayes were at an End? The Lord knew, this was &amp; is the very intent &amp; breathing
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:48840:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of my ſoul, and if this was Deluſion, I will be deluded more; for <hi>I</hi> am ſure God hath promiſed, <hi>Seek and you ſhall find, knock and it ſhall be opened;</hi> and do they ſay, this is but a Fancy and a Whimſie. And many times I have gone into the field, and I have got into a Land of Corn in private, when no Eye or Ear hath ſeen or heard me, and there have I kneeled down, and prayed and cryed to God, and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with him, as <hi>I</hi> was created, and he my Creator, and <hi>I</hi> had a ſoul to be ſaved, that he would not withhold himſelf from me; for I knew not any one living upon the Face of the whole Earth that I could have any Comfort in, if thou, O thou God of Heaven and Earth didſt not help me; and whither ſhould <hi>I</hi> go, or how ſhould <hi>I</hi> pray; for thou O God of Heaven and Earth. <hi>Haſt the Words of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life,</hi> and <hi>I</hi> ſhall not let thee reſt till thou haſt Mercy upon me; for I cannot truſt my Salvation upon this man's Faith, or the other man's Faith, but upon thee, O thou God of Heaven and Earth alone; and after this manner J went on.</p>
            <p>And J was a great lover of Muſick, and many times as J have been thinking of God, and of the Condition that J was in, it would have brought trouble upon me; ſo that many times I have took my <hi>Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern,</hi> or <hi>Treble Viol,</hi> or any inſtrument as I had moſt Delight in, thinking to drive away theſe Thoughts, and <hi>I</hi> have been ſo troubled, as <hi>I</hi> have been playing, that J have laid my inſtrument down, and have reaſoned with my ſelf after this manner, and fell a crying to God, it is true <hi>I</hi> love this Muſick, but what good can theſe ſounds do me when my ſoul wants Peace with God; and this doth but ſtir up Laughter, and Lightneſs of Spirit, to make me forget my Maker and this will <hi>I</hi> laſt but a little while, and <hi>I</hi> had better ſeek my Peace with God, and then, <hi>At his Right Hand there is Pleaſures for evermore;</hi> and theſe thoughts I had then: So that my Muſick began to be a Burden to me, and J would fain have ſold them, my Intruments, but that I had not Freedom in my Mind to do; for if J did, thoſe who bought them would have made uſe of them as <hi>I</hi> did, and J thought J would not be the Cauſe of it; ſo J took as many as <hi>I</hi> ſuppoſe coſt forty Shilling, and BURNED THEM, and had great Peace in my mind in doing of it, which is more to me then all the Pleaſures in this world: And often I have cried to God and ſaid as the Scriptures ſay, <hi>Thou art no Reſpecter of Perſons,</hi> though I am but a poor ſimple man, why may not <hi>I</hi> know as much of thee, as to my Salvation as another
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:48840:5"/>
man, ſince my Since<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ity is before thee, and thou ſeeſt what my Heart earneſtly breaths after; for it was not this Name, or that Name that I minded, but Peace with God, when my dayes were at an End.</p>
            <p>Then as to my Employment of <hi>Periwig making;</hi> it is more then twelve years ſince I began to make them &amp; much might be ſaid for the making of them by ſome, yet much queſtioning, &amp; reaſoning have I had within my ſelf for ſome years; ſo that at ſome times I have been trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled when I have been making of them, and I could not tell what was the Reaſon of my Trouble, except that was; and ſometimes when I have ſeen ſome of my Friends come in I have been ready to put them out of my ſight, and could not go on with any Content, but Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſo long as they were looking on me, and ſome have ſpoke to me, and told me, They thought I did not do well in making of them; &amp; to this purpoſe they have ſpoken, and many times I have reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with my ſelf after this manner, what need I make ſuch ado and be ſo much concerned, there is hardly any man but is deſirous of a good Head of Hair, and if Nature doth not afford it, if there be an Art to make a Decent Wig or Border, what harm is that<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But are there not ſeveral of thy Friends, who wear Borders, and are accounted honeſt men?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> As for thoſe whoſe Hair is waſted, fallen and gone off their Heads through infirmity of Body, and for want of it do find that their health is impaired, or leſſened, if ſuch do wear ſhort Borders ſo their health ſake, and for no other End or Cauſe whatſoever, I judge them not; but let none make a pretence that they wear Borders or Wigs for their Health, when in Reallity, another thing is the Cauſe, for God the Righteous Judge ſees in Secret, and he hates Pride &amp; Hypocriſie, the ſpirit of which is judged, &amp; for ever to be judg'd with all its fruits by the Lord and his People And let all thoſe who have Hair growing upon their heads, ſufficient to ſerve them, I mean what is really need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful or uſeful, be content therewith, and not find fault with their own Hair, and cut it off, and luſt after and put on others Hair.</p>
            <p>And further, thus I reaſoned, is there not ſome of thy Friends who make them; &amp; ſell Hair for the making of them, and drive a great Trade and what, do J not think that they have not as much Care to go to Heaven as J have, and what need J make ſuch ado, and be ſo concerned? But all this would not do, but here lay that which <hi>was very near me, that was, if God ſhould call me to account at this very time,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:48840:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
while J am reaſoning after this manner, whether or no J could ſtand clear in his ſight and make them;</hi> for if J ſtood condemned in God's ſight, it was not this man's making of them, nor the other man's wearing of them, that would juſtifie me in God's ſight; for if God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns me in my Conſcience, J know no man living, who can juſtifie or take away that Guilt: And here J ſtood in this Condition for ſome time; and the Lord knew the travel of my ſoul in theſe things, and J knew not what J ſhould do to be cleared of them, ſo that J have been almoſt out of Hopes, ſometime, and ſaid within my ſelf, and cried, J am afraid, J ſhall dye with this upon my Conſcience, and then what will become of me hereafter, and how can J ſtand clear in the ſight of God, that am condemned for it in my Conſcience? But my Prayers and Cryes were, for God to deliver me; for J could not deliver my ſelf out of it, but here J lay one day after another crying to God to be delivered: So ſuddenly after our dreadful fire, in which J was wi h the reſt of my Neighbours a Partaker of that Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, then J was more concerned then before; ſo that J knew not what to do, to get over it, it lay ſo hard upon me to bear: But ſtill this curſed Enemy of my Soul, this <hi>SELF-END Spirit,</hi> began to work with me again, and reaſon with me after this manner; what, am <hi>I</hi> reſolved to ruin my ſelf, and turn away all; if J do leave this, J muſt expect to loſe a great deal of my <hi>Trimming Trade</hi> and J had better leave off that, then leave off this Periwig-making; it fits ſo well with me in the Condition J am in, by Reaſon of my Lameneſs: J had a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Trade in it with ſeveral of my Acquaintance in Town and Country, and ſome of them are Perſons of Quality, and wiſh me very well, and if J leave that J ſhall diſoblige them much, and what will J do then? am J minded to undo my ſelf? But ſtill there was an inward Cry in me, <hi>Lord ſave my ſoul;</hi> for that lies at ſtake, and it is that J plead for, and J care not what J go through, ſo my ſoul may have Peace with thee, when my dayes are at an End; for my ſoul is for Everlaſting, but this Trouble cannot laſt long: Theſe things ſtuck very hard with me, that made me cry out night and day, <hi>Lord deliver me, and help me over this Weight and Pain that is upon my Spirit, and J care not what J do ſo J may be clear of them:</hi> So through much TROUBLE OF SPIRIT J was willing to leave them: But this would not clear me, but as I had been a publick Profeſſor of this Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for ſome time, I muſt bear my Teſtimony againſt them; and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:48840:6"/>
that was, I ſhould ſend for my two men, as I had inſtructed in that way, and tell them how <hi>I</hi> was troubled, and take a Wig and burn it before them, as a Teſtimony for God againſt them: But this was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hard, but no Peace could I have before I did it, and much Pain and Sorrow I had before I did it: and no Comfort, but Torment of mind I had till I had given up to do it; ſo according to the Pain and Sorrow that lay hard upon me <hi>I</hi> gave up to do it, and I thank God, I have much Eaſe &amp; Comfort of Mind ſince <hi>I</hi> have done it for the Lord hath not put me upon any thing, but what he hath given me ſtrength to go through, and he is not a hard Maſter, and I have great Peace and Comfort in what I have done, which is more to me then all the Periſhing, Fading things in this world: And whoever he be that doth expect Peace with God in himſelf, he muſt know a Croſs to his own Will, to croſs his ſinful thoughts, Words and Actions; and whatever he knows God requires of him, he muſt do it, though it be a great Croſs to him, though it is very hard to Fleſh and Blood; <hi>Fleſh and Blood cannot inherit the Kingdom of Heaven; but a man muſt be born again:</hi> And as truly it is witneſſed, as ever it was writ in the Scripture; God's People this day do know this ſpiritual Birth, Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be God for ever; and they travel in Spirit till God gives Encreaſe and delivers them: And I am ſure, and can ſpeak by Experience, I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver met with a better Friend in all my Life, then the Spirit of God; for it never croſſeth that which is according to God's Will, but if God's Will be not done, this Spirit brings Pain and Trouble upon the Soul, if it be minded.</p>
            <p>So <hi>I</hi> would deſire any ingenuous ſober Reader, without Prejudice to judge, if it had been their own Caſe, whether they would not have left off this Employment of <hi>Periwig-making,</hi> rather then to have went on with ſo much Condemnation in themſelves; and theſe be the Reaſons and Occaſions why I left them off: And now, you my lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Neighbours and Acquaintance, I would not have you think, that how I have denyed my ſelf, and took up this Croſs, as to come among his poor ſcorned People, and left off my <hi>Muſick</hi> which was a great Delight to me; and likewiſe this Employment of <hi>Periwig-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king,</hi> which <hi>I</hi> have told you was ſo hard for me to part with, that now <hi>I</hi> think my ſelf ſafe enough; No, God is my witneſs this day, from whom <hi>I</hi> have my Breath &amp; Being, I have as much need of keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my Mind ſtaid upon God, as ever I had in all my dayes: And
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:48840:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
whatever I have done, it is no more but my Duty to God, to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer his Requirings in my Conſcience; and here I lie ſtill upon the Free Mercies of God, through his Grace in his Son Chriſt Jeſus my Saviour to be ſaved; and I care not what <hi>I</hi> go through for Chriſt's ſake: And here I find a Preſſing forward to the Mark of the Price of the high Calling which is in Chriſt Jeſus: And at the end <hi>I</hi> do not queſtion, as I keep faithful to God, I ſhall obtain the Salvation of my Soul, and that is enough.</p>
            <p>And whereas there is moſt dreadful ſpeeches caſt againſt this poor, ſcorned and ſcoffed People of God, who are called <hi>Quakers,</hi> as if they had their very Principle from the darkeſt Hell; and ſome have told me, They come from the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> and <hi>Papiſts;</hi> and very ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dly peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple have ſpoken concering them: But truly Neighbours and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, I would intreat you to let me ſpeak in this matter, and I hope I have not behaved my ſelf ſo badly amongſt you, for almoſt this twenty years, but I may have a little C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>edit for what I ſay: So long as I have come amongſt them, which I think is 13 or 14 years I never underſtood any ſuch thing, but the very main Aim that they have and do drive at, is to have People be faithful to God in what they know in themſelves; and this is that plain down right way they have drove at and do, and God hath proſpered them and will do: let all thoſe that are Oppoſers of this Principle of God, do what they can: They can as well ſtop the Sun from ſhining, the Rain from falling as hinder this ſpiritual work from proſpering in the Hearts of his People; for it is beyond the ſtrength of man to hinder it: They were not ſet up by man nor can man pull them down. And as for the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> and <hi>Papiſts,</hi> I know not what they are as to their Principles, neither indeed do I deſire to know, but thoſe that are not as they ſhould be, I deſire the Lord may make them ſo. But as to my own part, <hi>I</hi> will tell you what my Faith is, and what I do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, call me what you pleaſe, nor <hi>I</hi> never deſired to believe other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe: That is <hi>I do believe in God, who is the Father Almighty, Maker of Heaven &amp; Earth and in Jeſus Chriſt his only Son, our Lord, who was concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the holy Ghoſt; born of the</hi> Virgin Mary; <hi>and that he did ſuffer under</hi> Pontius Pilate, <hi>and the third day he roſe again from the dead, and ſits at the Right Hand of God his Father, who ſhall judge both the quick and the dead;</hi> and I do believe, that <hi>God hath a Church, where there is the Communion of Saints in his Spirit and Power;</hi> and I do believe <hi>The For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:48840:7"/>
of Sins, the Reſurrection of the Body, and Everlaſting Life,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Teſtimony recorded in the holy Scriptures: but indeed, <hi>I</hi> do not believe thar at your publick Places of Worſhip, that this is the Church of God, nor your Aſſemblies are the Communion of Saints; for it is not the Saints Life, to live in Curſing and Swearing, in Pride and Drunkenneſs, in Envy and Malice, Hatred and Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, &amp;c. but in the Spirit of Truth, which leads into all Truth: But alas! what of all theſe Evils is there not committed in this age amongſt thoſe that do aſſemble themſelves together, in your Publick Aſſemblies, where there is ſo many Prayers of, <hi>Good Lord deliver us from them;</hi> which <hi>I</hi> ſay, <hi>I</hi> am a witneſs for God, he ſtands ready to deliver you, if you will come to him; <hi>But you will not come to him that you may have Life,</hi> John 5.39. And again, the Saints do not believe, that Chriſt Jeſus the Son of the living God, did pray to his Father to put his poor Creatures upon thoſe things which were impoſſible to be done; for when he wiſhed his Diſciples to pray, he ſaid to them, <hi>Pray thus, Our Father which art in Heaven, hallowed be thy Name, thy King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom com, thy Will be done in Earth as it is in Heaven,</hi> and ſo forth. Now ſome among you ſay, God's Will cannot be done here, we muſt live in ſin ſo long as we live <hi>[There is no Freedom from ſin on this ſide the Grave, no Peace with God to be known here]</hi> Oh! what a damnable Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine is this; if men would but plead for God's Kingdom, as they do for the Devil's, and would but believe that God was as able through the Light and Life of his Son Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.10: <hi>For if when we were Enemies, we were reconciled to God, by the Death of his Son: much more being reconciled, we ſhall be ſaved by his Life.</hi> To ſave them from their ſins, as the Devil was to keep them in their ſins, we ſhould have brave living; and yet all will ſay, God is above the Devil.</p>
            <p>For the Lord ſake, Neighbours and Acquaintance, conſider theſe things; for God is my witneſs this day, <hi>I</hi> plead not with you for your ſilver nor your gold, nor for any thing that you have in this world, but beſeech you to be reconciled to the Principle of God in your Conſcience: And how many Scriptures is there to perſwade you to a Holy Life, as <hi>Without Holineſs none ſhall ſee God.</hi> Heb. 12.10. <hi>For they verily for a few dayes chaſtened us after their own Pleaſure, but he for our Profit, that we might be Partakers of his Holineſs. Except a man be born again, he cannot enter into the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> John 3.3. <hi>We know that whoſoever is born of God, ſinneth not: But he that is begotten of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:48840:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
God, keepeth himſelf, and that Wicked one toucheth him not. Be ye therefore Perfect, even as your Father which is in Heaven is Perfect</hi> Mat 5.18. And many more Places to this purpoſe, and yet you ſay, the Scripture muſt be your rule, ſee how contrary you walk to it, and ſay it is impoſſible to be done; and Chriſt he ſaid, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.14. <hi>Becauſe ſtrait is the Gate, and narrow is the Way which leadeth unto Life, and few there be that find it.</hi> The Saints they were perſecuted and impriſoned, and Chriſt ſaid, <hi>For if they do theſe things in a green Tree, what ſhall be done in the dry?</hi> Luke 23.31. <hi>If they perſecuted me, they will perſecute you alſo; if they regarded not my Sayings, they will not regard yours:</hi> I pray you do but look back, which look more like Saints, thoſe as aſſemble themſelves together in your Aſſemblies, or theſe whom Chriſt ſpake of, who are perſecuted for Righteouſneſs ſake; and truly <hi>I</hi> look upon theſe to be <hi>Real Saints,</hi> and had rather take my Portion among ſuch in this day, if it be in Perſecution, then to enjoy the Pleaſures of ſin for a ſeaſon. And when <hi>I</hi> came amongſt this People at firſt; what a ſtrangeneſs did it Cauſe amongſt my very Relations and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, inſomuch that my neareſt Relations were ſtirred up, in Env<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd Bitterneſs againſt me, ſome ſignifying as if I had not been fit to live upon the Earth; and the Lord knows, I had no other De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire in my Heart, but to do that which my <hi>God-fathers</hi> &amp; <hi>God-mothers,</hi> as they call them, promiſed <hi>I</hi> ſhould do, as is the Cuſtom now adays, which People talk of; but if they come to do it, they riſe up as an Army againſt them, Father againſt the Son, and Daughter againſt the Mother, and <hi>All Evil-doers</hi> againſt Chriſt's Appearances ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually, ſo that in effect they ſay, <hi>They will not have this man to rule o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver us:</hi> and whoever he be that is a true ſpiritual Traveller, will find theſe things to be true: And that was, <hi>That I ſhould forſake the Devil and all his works, the vain Pomps and Vanities of this wicked world, the ſinful luſts of the fleſh,</hi> and ſo forth; but as long as I could talk of theſe things, and not do them, no notice was took of me, as to be offended with me; but when I came to do theſe things, what a do was here, and whath ſtrangeneſs did it beget amomgſt my ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry familiar Acquaintance! And God is my witneſs, at this time it is the very end of my Travel in Spirit<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>To make my Peace with God when my dayes are at an end.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now Neighbours and Acquaint<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>I</hi> being one that have had hard ſpeeches caſt upon me by ſome of you, <hi>I</hi> thought <hi>I</hi> could
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:48840:8"/>
not be clear in the ſight of God and man, till I had acquainted you how it was with me from a Child to this day, which I hope will give no occaſion of Offence to any; but could heartily wiſh, that you may not be alwayes Profeſſors, but Poſſeſſors of that Life which is beyond all the Profeſſion in the world; and that you may know the Lord's will to be done in your hearts, as it is in Heaven, and then you will pray as you ſhould do, and know what to pray for: And truly my loving Neighbours and Acquaintance, if it had been poſſible for you to have ſeen the inſide of me, <hi>I</hi> have told you the very Travel of my ſoul in theſe things, and what I have here will I have had the Experience of; and do not think it is a Whimſie, or a Fancy and a Deluſion to ſerve God: it is your Concern as well as mine, your ſouls lie in danger of Ruin as well as mine hath done, and therefore for the Lord's ſake conſider theſe things, which belong to your everlaſting peace, before they be hid from your Eyes; for here is but a little while before your dayes be at an End, and we ſhall ſee man no more, and what is all this world worth then? it is not all the words of earthly wiſemen, though called Teaches of this age or any man that can juſtifie you, if God condemn you by his Light and Spirit in your own hearts; the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>efore for the Lord's ſake, think not that God will be mocked, nor make not ſleight of theſe things; for ſuch as you ſow you muſt reap: Your ſouls lie in danger of ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Miſery, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it is an inward Reformation, a new heart, a ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ht ſpirit as God looks for of us all: and it is the earneſt Breathing of my ſoul, you may ſeek after it, as well as myſelf.</p>
            <p>And now, you my loving Neighbours and Acquaintance of this Town of <hi>Northampton,</hi> where among you I have drawn my firſt breath, how hath my heart been pained, to behold the Ruins of this poor Town, and I have and do from my very ſoul deſire, that this Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction which God hath ſent amongſt us may be for the better, and not for the worſe: And it is not long ſince there was another warning by Thunder, Lightning and Hail-ſtorm, ſuch that in all my daye, I do not know I have heard or ſeen the like; what Dread and Fear were the poor Inhabitants in at that time? Oh that you would have kept your minds exerciſed as I do beleive ſome did, and had ſome Senſe of the Dread <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Fear of this Terrible God, that can ſhake terribly the Earth, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>make the Inhabitants fear b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fore him!</hi> I ſay what Fear were they in at that time, running up and down, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:48840:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
that the Town had been fired by Reaſon of the Lightning that was at that time? The Lord grant that you may be of that Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple or Religion, as it hath been my deſire from a Child to be of that Religion which would endure a Thunder-clap, that is, if God ſhould have called me or you to Judgment at that very time, we might be ready with Oyl in our Lamps; and not Put it off to buy when the Bridgroom comes; for bleſſed be God, at that very time, I do not ſpeak it for any Praiſe among you, God is my witneſs, but as <hi>I</hi> felt it upon my Spirit at that very time; I could ſing for Joy in my Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, when others were running up and down in Dread and Fear; and for ever my ſoul ſhall truſt in this God, who is mighty to ſave, and mighty to deſtroy, God bleſſed forever: And the very Inhabitants themſelves could not but at that time confeſs, that God had ſent another Judgment amongſt them, in my hearing; but yet for all this, what blaſPheming the Name of God is here, and Drunkenneſs and all manner of Wickedneſs almoſt, committed, Envy, Malice and Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, and what not, inſomuch that ſome have told me ſeveral times, that you think in your Conſcience, you are a great deal worſe then you were before the Fire, and why is it ſo with you, for the Lord's ſake conſider, what will become of you that go on in this reſolute way; God will not alwayes ſtrive with you; put not (<hi>I</hi> beſeech you) this day of the Lord afar off, but while it ts to day, harden not your Hearts: <hi>I</hi> would intreat you that you would look back, for about this twenty years, what have this poor, ſcorned People of God cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Quakers</hi> preached amongſt you, but this principle, to have Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple mind God in their Conſcience, and to be faithful to what they know of God; and what hard meaſure have they met with? how have they been ſtocked and ſtoned, and whipped and impriſoned, their Goods rended from them, and for nothing but for God's ſake, to keep their Conſcience clear in his ſight? And how have ſome ſeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it with their Blood, and ſtill are ready, though patient Suffering in his Power, God be magnified for it, with their Lives given up, and if God ſhould ſuffer them to be brought to the ſtake for the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of Jeſus: And let the Rain fall, and the Wind blow; and the Storms beat, they are anchored upon that Rock Chriſt Jeſus, which the Gates of Hell cannot prevail againſt: And do not think, that this Pearl of great price, which they have ſold all for, they will part with for nothing, or for the Glory of this World, which pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſheth:
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:48840:9"/>
and this I ſay of them, that are faithful to God in what they know, they are the People of God, and there is no more required of any of us, but to be faithful to what we know, be it much or little. So this is my Teſtimony for this people, if I ſhould write no more; for <hi>I</hi> wait for my Diſſolution, nor I know not how few my dayes may be amongſt you.</p>
            <p>And now, you my loving Neighbours and Acqaintance, ſince it hath been the Good Pleaſure of the God of Heaven<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to ſend this Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction of Lameneſs upon me, ſo that in the prime of my age, my ſtrength is taken from me; I Care not charge God with Injuſtice; nor murmure againſt him; he is Juſt and Righteous in all his wayes, and if he had not ſent this Affliction upon me, I know not whether <hi>I</hi> ſhould have been conformable to his Heavenly Will; but in Love and Tenderneſs to my ſoul hath he ſuffered this Exerciſe to come upon me, and I have for ever Cauſe to bleſs his Name, that ever he hath dealt with me after this manner, if he never reſtore me to my former ſtrength again, his Will be done, though to look at it, it is very hard, and <hi>I</hi> know, I am an Object of Pity to many of you; but why ſhould I murmur at it? <hi>Shall the Pot ſay to the Potter why haſt thou made me thus?</hi> No I ſhall not, but bleſs his Name, that ever he hath ſpared me to this day, that I ſhould anſwer what he required of this poor weak Body of mine; and this is the greateſt Joy and Comfort of my Soul, that as I have found my ſtrength go from me outwardly, my Faith, and Hope, and Strength hath renewed in God inwardly: And here I have great Cauſe of Joy and Comfort, and to God let the Honour and Praiſe be, who is worthy overall bleſſed for ever, and for evermore faith my ſoul.</p>
            <p>And one thing more I would deſire of you, to have a Care of ſpeaking ſlightingly of the Spirit of God and Chriſt, and making a Mock thereat, as ſome have done, as ſaying, <hi>What the Spirit will not let you do this or that?</hi> Let me prevail with you, to have a Care what you ſay, as to this thing, leſt you ſin the unpardonable ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt. I have wondered when ſome men have ſpoke to me after this manner, who profeſs to be VViſe and Religious, ſhould offer to ſpeak ſo ſlightingly of this Spiritual Appearance of Chriſt; for if ever you know God, you muſt know him Spiritually; <hi>For God is a Spirit, and they that worſhlp him muſt worſhip him in Spirit and in Truth:</hi> And do you not read, how <hi>The Spirit wars againſt the fleſh, and the fleſh
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:48840:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
againſt the Spirit: And to be ſpiritually minded is Life and Peace, but to be carnally minded is Death.</hi> And again. <hi>Quench not the Spirit; Grieve not the Holy Spirit, whereby ye are ſealed unto the day of Redemption,</hi> Eph. 4.30. <hi>And it ſhall come to paſs afterward, that I will pour out my ſpirit upon all fleſh; and your ſons and your daughters ſhall propheſie, your old men ſhall dream dreams, your young men ſhall ſee viſions</hi> Joel 2.28 And ſeveral more Scriptures there are that we may read, concerning their ſpiritual Conditions; but this ſpiritual Appearance of Chriſt is ſo mocked and ſcorned at, that when any of God's People are brought before ſome, you are ready to ſay, what, you are troubled with he Spirit, you cannot ſwear, you cannot give us Reſpect<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> you muſt come with theeing &amp; thouing in your mouths, and be brought before whom you will all is one to you: Bleſſed be God that it is ſo, that there is a, People have more regard to pleaſe God, then to pleaſe any man living as to theſe things: Some time <hi>I</hi> have had concerns wi h ſome of you, that rather then I would have come before you with my hat on, if <hi>I</hi> could have been clear in God's ſight, <hi>I</hi> had rather have lain at your Feet; but at any time, if <hi>I</hi> did not ſtand faithful to this ſmall thing as you count of, what Pain and Sorrow have I had quickly after it in my Conſcience, that <hi>I</hi> knew I had not done well in it, and it hath cauſed me to cry ſometimes to God, ſurely <hi>I</hi> ſhall take more care next time.</p>
            <p>Now if you would but keep to your rule the Scriptures, as you rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon them, methinks you need not be ſo much offended, whenas the Scriptures ſpeak againſt having men's Perſons in Admiration, becauſe of Advantage; <hi>He that reſpects mens Perſons commits ſin:</hi> Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Learn of me, I am meek and lowly, and you ſhall find reſt to your ſouls;</hi> Who learns Lowlineſs of him will not take Offence at thoſe who in Obedience to him, ſpeak his Language [<hi>Thee and Thou</hi> to a ſingle Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and who wear their Hats upon their Heads, for which they were made. If men would but truly come to ſerve the Lord their God in their Hearts, it would teach them better manners one to another, then a few diſſembling Titles of Honour; and worſhipful with the Cap and Knee; I pray you what do they all ſignifie, but to make men proud, amd there is too much of that already? But this let them do, <hi>Do-juſtly, love Mercy, and walk humbly with their God,</hi> and then there will be no Offence taken. And why ſhould you take Occaſion at <hi>Thee</hi> or <hi>Thou?</hi> in the Scripture you may plentifully ſee, that when the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:48840:10"/>
Servants of God went to declare his VVord to the Kings, they went and ſaid, <hi>Thou O King, hear the Word of the L rd;</hi> and in your very Prayers when you pray to God, do you not ſay, <hi>Thou Lord,</hi> or <hi>Thou God?</hi> And what, do you expect better Language then you give to the God of Heaven, which if you ſhould ſay <hi>[You]</hi> it would be Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſe, and People would think ſuch were not in their wits, as ſhould ſay <hi>[You Lord]</hi> or <hi>[You God.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then again this Rule ſaith, that formerly it was ſaid in the time of the Law, <hi>Thou ſhalt not forſwear thy ſelf;</hi> but Chriſt, <hi>Who is the end of the Law for Righteousneſs ſake, to every one that believeth,</hi> Rom. 10.4.) ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all, but let your Yea be Yea, and your Nay be Nay,</hi> Mat. 5.34. And <hi>James</hi> ſaith, <hi>Above all things my Brethren, ſwear not,</hi> Jam. 5.12. And now you can make ſome by your Law, pay for ſwearing, and others have got money by ſwearing, and others you would force contrary to the Command of Chriſt, and their Conſcience, to ſwear; and becauſe they would not ſwear, they have been impriſoned, ſome until death, and I pray you do but ſee what Confuſion here is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you. Much more might be ſaid from ſeveral Places of the holy Sc iptures, as to the preſſing of you to a holy, godly living, but many o you will not, but even <hi>Hate to be reformed. I</hi> verily think, there may be ſome that are tender hearted, that have a Love for God, but yet to leave all the Glory and Vanities of the world, and deny themſelves to <hi>Follow him,</hi> appears to them very hard; but this you muſt do, fever you know Peace with God: And as ſure as ever the Scriptures declare of it; for as Chriſt ſaid, <hi>He that loveth any thing more then me, is not worthy of me:</hi> For verily, <hi>I</hi> do look upon it to be man's greateſt Happineſs and Felicity to be a true Servant of Gold, and the moſt Honourableſt Title in the VVorld, to be a true Chriſtian; for their Name is had in everlaſting Remembrance, when the Name of the wicked ſhall not: and therefore let them mock and ſcorn if they will, the day will come that God will clear the Innocency of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and think not that it is impoſſible to know God as his People did formerly, when it was ſaid, that they <hi>Did taſte and ſee how good the Lord was;</hi> and they <hi>Taſted and Handled of the Good Word of Life:</hi> And do not think it is enough to believe as <hi>Your Church</hi> believes, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe your Anceſto s went in this way, you may; and what ſhould you trouble your ſelves any further; and truly, if I could have been ſatisfied here my ſelf, I would willingly have went along with you,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:48840:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
but I could not, though many times with Tears I have cryed to God and ſaid, why cannot <hi>I</hi> be ſatisfied to do as ſuch, who are eſteemed wiſe, underſtanding men, that I muſt ſeparate from them, and become a Scoff and a Scorn to them, but bleſſed be God, he hath made known himſelf ſpiritually to a little Remnant, who have followed him through the great Tribulations; and bleſſed be his Name for ever, he hath confirmed the Truth of it to this poor People under his hand and ſeal, as it were, by his eternal Spirit; ſo that they do taſte and handle of this good VVord of Life, as they keep faithful to him in what they know; for no more God requires of me nor you: for if it but one Talent, if we keep faithful and improve it, it was ſaid, <hi>Well done, faithful Servant, thou haſt been faithful in a little, I will make thee Ruler over much; enter thou into the Joy of the L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rd:</hi> So it is Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfulneſs to God as is curſed in the inward parts.</p>
            <p>The Lord give you an Underſtanding of theſe things is my earneſt Deſire; for God is my witneſs, I have no ill will to any of you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but my earneſt Deſire is for you as for my own ſelf, to pray and beſeech you to be reconciled to God, and not to grieve and quench his Holy Spirit in your Conſciences, by living in known ſin and tranſgreſſion; for who ever they be that will not accept of Mercy, they muſt expect Judgment; for God is Juſt and Righteous in all his wayes, and he will and hath been clear of the Blood of all People in a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l Ages and Generations that are gone: And therefore for the Lord's ſake and our own ſouls ſake, let us not ſlight Chriſt's ſpiritual Appearance in our Conſcience, but be perſwaded to let him have the whole Heart; for it is an inſide work: And whoever he be, if he hath never ſo eloquent a Declaration at preaching, let him profeſs what he will, if it be the Truth it ſelf, let him preach and pray, ſing Pſalms and Hymns; if they be not ſpirtual, they are as if they cut of a Dog's Neck, and as ſounding Braſs and tinkling Cymbal in the ſight of God and no Profit in them at all.</p>
            <p>So this is my Teſtimony for God, that he doth appear as he is <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritualy</hi> and do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h more and more appear by the Light of his Son Chriſt Jeſus in the He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rts of this poor ſcorned People called <hi>Quakers,</hi> as ſure as ever Chriſt did appear <hi>Perſonally</hi> upon the Earth to his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, according to the Holy Scriptures of Truth; And therefore ſligh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not this ſpiritual Appearance of Chriſt I beſeech you, that which condemns you for ſin in your Conſciences, as you ten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:48840:11"/>
welfare of your immortal ſouls, and though this come from a ſimple Inſtrument, yet I would intreat you to bear with me; for it is in Love to you all.</p>
            <p>And before ever I ſet Pen to paper to write this, I have in the very ſecret of my ſoul deſired, that <hi>I</hi> might have lain in a Cave in the ground and have cried out theſe few dayes <hi>I</hi> have here upon the Earth, to the Lord, rather then <hi>I</hi> would have appeared ſo openly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you, but <hi>I</hi> could not be clear till I had ſignified my mind to you; and ſo <hi>I</hi> do appeal to the Principle of God in all your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences; I being one that have had my being amongſt you almoſt all my dayes, what damnable Practice or Principle have any of you ſeen by me, that makes you talk at this rate? Except you call this damnable which checks and reproves you when you do not well; and which of you all dare to ſay, he hath it not in him? which is the great Love of God unto Mankind, which doth either excuſe, or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe, if they do good or evil; and this is that Witneſs that God hath not left himſelf without, in the hearts of all Mankind.</p>
            <p>And certainly, if there had been any thing in your Teachers Doctrines, Reaſons, Uſes and Applications; if Crying and Tears, Sighs and Groans would afforded me any Comfort in them, the Lord would have ſatisfied me in them; but I could not get Peace in them, though the Lord knows it was my daily Prayers from a Child, to be ſatisfied: And therefore, having dealt plainly wtih you, and having told you how it was with me from my Childhood, do you think that I am deluded, and do you think that <hi>I</hi> with many more that have known this ſpiritual Travel, will be ſcoffed and ſcorned out of this experienced Principle of God in our Conſciences? my God be bleſſed, we know better things: And though you may <hi>Goliah</hi> like, come in defiance againſt this Hoſt of the Living God, yet be it known to you, <hi>You are but men, and not Gods,</hi> and though we are but poor Striplings, and ſimple. Mecanick, poor Tradeſmen, and ſome coming from their flocks and herds: We do not encounter with you, with Swords or Spears; but in the Name of the Lord we go on, and here the Lord hath given ſtrength and patience to ſuffer, whatever hath come up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his poor People, for the trial of their Faith: So that <hi>They are more then Conquerers, through him that hath loved them,</hi> as above twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Years Experience can witneſs, ſince the Lord firſt brought them forth, out of this Northern Part of this Nation; and this is that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:48840:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Lamb's Spirit in which we war, of which God hath ſaid, <hi>Shall have the Victory,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And do not think tis <hi>Excommunication,</hi> or rending our Goods from us, or Baniſhment, or any other thing, that ſhall be ever able <hi>To ſeparate us from the Love of God which is in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord:</hi> And, if Chriſt be not <hi>In <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s, we are Reprobates;</hi> and if it were not that this Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God were in us, and if we did not know and enjoy ſomething that was above this world, we were of all people, as the Scripture ſaith, <hi>Of all men in the World, the moſt miſerable:</hi> For indeed, the Caſe is God's, as we are concerned in, and if he doth not carry it on in us, we cannot go any further; and this is that City that God hath ſet on a Hill, which cannot he hid: For alas, <hi>Our Profeſſion</hi> is as emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty as any Profeſſion, if we find not this Principle of God in our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, to proſper, which teacheth us to deny all Ungodlineſs: and if it be but a Sigh, or a Groan, a Cry, or a Tear, that cometh from an Honeſt Heart, God hath regard to it; for alas, though there may be tricks that men may ſhufle or cut one with another, we cannot deal ſo with this Alſeeing God, with whom we have to do; for alas, without God we can do nothing, therefore it is to this Principle in your Conſciences I direct you; for no further then you find me plead for God, no longer own me.</p>
            <p>My Neighbours and Acquaintance of this Town of <hi>Northampton, I</hi> pray you, do you but a little conſider what Condition were you in ſuddenly after this Judgment of God that was amongſt us by Fire, at which time we met one another, ſeveral with Tears in their Eyes, telling one another of their Loſſes by this ſad Judgment! Oh what a tender Frame of Spirit were many of you in then! O that you had kept to that! and it would have been greatly for your good: for then you would have gone forward in that which is good, till you had found Reconciliation and Eſtabliſhment with your Maker, and you would have remembred his Judgments and Mercy, &amp; have ſpoken of them to his Praiſe; but how little is this minded now! So that many live as if there were no God! To hear the great Abominations that are committed in your ſtreets is a greif to he upright now as ſuch things were a grief to the upright in all ages. Oh that theſe things may be conſidered, laid to heart &amp; amended therefore it be too late; for our days are ſwiftly paſſing over, <hi>as a Weavers Shuttle, and as a tale that is told.</hi> The Lord grant that unto this Humble, tender Frame of Spirit you
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:48840:12"/>
may come, and not let thoſe former Afflictions ſlip out of your Remembrance; for God hath promiſed, he will <hi>Not break the bruiſed Reed, nor quench the ſmoaking Flax,</hi> but if your <hi>Sins were as Scarlet, he would make them as wooll, if as Crimſon, he would make them as Snow,</hi> and this is the Lord's doing, and it is marvelous in our Eye; and this is that humble way that my ſoul hath found Favour with him, and for ever my ſoul ſhall praiſe him. And I know not how few my dayes may be amongſt you yet this is my Teſtimony and my Belief concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this People, thoſe of them as are faithful, <hi>I</hi> could wiſh <hi>I</hi> could ſay ſo for all as are called ſo, that they are the People of God. So whether you will be reconciled to this Princip e of God in your Conſcience or no, <hi>I</hi> am clear in my ſelf concerning you.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Who am a Well-wiſher to your immortal Souls, John Mulliner.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:48840:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
